<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<front xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <journal-meta>
    <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">2697-3650</journal-id>
    <journal-title-group>
      <journal-title>Blensera</journal-title>
      <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">BRC</abbrev-journal-title>
    </journal-title-group>
    <issn pub-type="epub">2697-3650</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>Ediciones Universidad del Salvador</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Ciudad de Buenos aires, Argentina</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
  </journal-meta>
  <article-meta>
    <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18356/9789210029582c005</article-id>
    <article-categories>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
        <subject>research-article</subject>
      </subj-group>
    </article-categories>
    <title-group>
      <article-title>Desigualdad digital y rendimiento académico en la educación superior: un estudio comparativo en universidades públicas de Argentina y México</article-title>
      <trans-title-group xml:lang="en">
        <trans-title>The digital divide and academic performance in higher education: a comparative study in public universities of Argentina and Mexico</trans-title>
      </trans-title-group>
    </title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="author" id="a3">
        <name>
          <surname>Berreta Invernizzi</surname>
          <given-names>Georgina</given-names>
        </name>
        <aff>
          <city>Buenos Aires</city>,
          <country>Argentina</country>
        </aff>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
      <year>2026</year>
      <month>06</month>
      <day>30</day>
    </pub-date>
    <volume>01</volume>
    <issue>01</issue>
    <history>
      <date date-type="rev-recd">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>06</month>
        <year>2026</year>
      </date>
      <date date-type="pub">
        <day>01</day>
        <month>07</month>
        <year>2026</year>
      </date>
    </history>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-year>2026</copyright-year>
      <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licences/by-nc.nd/4.0">
        <license-p>CC BY-NC-ND- 4.0</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <abstract xml:lang="es">
      <p>Desigualdad digital y rendimiento académico en la educación superior

Este estudio analiza cómo influyen las condiciones de acceso digital en el rendimiento académico de estudiantes de grado en dos de las universidades públicas más grandes de América Latina: la Universidad de Buenos Aires (UBA, Argentina) y la Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México (UNAM, México). Con un enfoque mixto que combinó una encuesta a 1.247 alumnos y 40 entrevistas en profundidad, la investigación evalúa la desigualdad digital a través de cuatro niveles: motivacional, material, de habilidades y de resultados.

Hallazgos principales

El estudio demuestra que tener internet o una computadora no garantiza el éxito académico por sí solo. El predictor más fuerte del rendimiento escolar son las **habilidades digitales** ($\beta = 0,34$), las cuales funcionan como un puente o variable mediadora: los estudiantes con mejor entorno material desarrollan competencias más complejas, lo que directamente se traduce en mejores calificaciones y avance en sus carreras.

Las pautas de desigualdad son sorprendentemente idénticas en Argentina y México, evidenciando que la brecha responde a factores socioeconómicos estructurales de la región y no a particularidades locales.

La brecha material en datos

Al segmentar a la población estudiantil por quintiles de ingreso (donde Q1 es el 20% más vulnerable y Q5 el 20% de mayores ingresos), las diferencias en la calidad del acceso son drásticas en ambas instituciones:

| Indicador de Acceso Material | UBA (Q1) | UBA (Q5) | UNAM (Q1) | UNAM (Q5) |
| --- | --- | --- | --- | --- |
| **Acceso a computadora** | 42,3% | 96,1% | 38,7% | 94,5% |
| **Conexión fija (fibra/cable)** | 51,8% | 93,4% | 35,2% | 91,8% |
| **Espacio privado de estudio** | 28,6% | 87,9% | 24,1% | 85,3% |
| **Velocidad de internet $\ge$ 20 Mbps** | 23,1% | 88,2% | 18,4% | 86,7% |

Mientras que los estudiantes de altos ingresos gozan de un acceso material prácticamente universal, los sectores vulnerables enfrentan limitaciones severas. No se trata solo de estar &quot;conectados&quot;, sino de las restricciones cualitativas del entorno.

El impacto en la vida cotidiana

La investigación cualitativa arrojó luz sobre las estrategias que implementan los alumnos afectados por estas brechas:

Gestión del ancho de banda: Negociar los horarios de uso familiar de internet, tomar clases con la cámara apagada para ahorrar datos o descargar lecturas de madrugada.
Restricciones de pantalla: Quienes dependen exclusivamente de teléfonos móviles reportan serias dificultades para la redacción de trabajos extensos, la consulta simultánea de fuentes y el manejo de gestores bibliográficos, lo que impacta en la calidad de sus entregas.

Conclusión y desafíos de política pública

Los resultados confirman que las políticas de inclusión universitaria orientadas únicamente a repartir computadoras o dar conectividad básica son insuficientes. Para que la digitalización y la educación híbrida no se conviertan en un filtro que amplifique las desigualdades de origen, las instituciones deben diseñar estrategias pedagógicas integrales que capaciten en competencias digitales informacionales y estratégicas, adaptándose a la realidad heterogénea de sus comunidades.</p>
    </abstract>
    <trans-abstract xml:lang="en">
      <p>Digital Inequality and Academic Performance in Higher Education

This study analyzes how digital access conditions influence the academic performance of undergraduate students at two of the largest public universities in Latin America: the University of Buenos Aires (UBA, Argentina) and the National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM, Mexico). Using a mixed-methods approach that combined a survey of 1,247 students with 40 in-depth interviews, the research evaluates digital inequality across four levels: motivational, material, skills, and outcomes.

Key Findings

The study demonstrates that simply having internet access or a computer does not guarantee academic success. The strongest predictor of academic performance is **digital skills** ($\beta = 0.34$), which function as a bridge or mediating variable: students with better material environments develop more complex competencies, which directly translates into better grades and academic progress.

The patterns of inequality are remarkably identical in both Argentina and Mexico, proving that the divide responds to structural socioeconomic factors within the region rather than local particularities.

The Material Divide in Data

When segmenting the student population by income quintiles (where Q1 represents the lowest 20% and Q5 the highest 20%), the differences in the quality of access are drastic in both institutions:

| Material Access Indicator | UBA (Q1) | UBA (Q5) | UNAM (Q1) | UNAM (Q5) |
| --- | --- | --- | --- | --- |
| **Computer access** | 42.3% | 96.1% | 38.7% | 94.5% |
| **Fixed connection (fiber/cable)** | 51.8% | 93.4% | 35.2% | 91.8% |
| **Private study space** | 28.6% | 87.9% | 24.1% | 85.3% |
| **Internet speed $\ge$ 20 Mbps** | 23.1% | 88.2% | 18.4% | 86.7% |

While high-income students enjoy virtually universal material access, vulnerable sectors face severe limitations. It is not just a matter of being &quot;connected,&quot; but rather about the qualitative restrictions of their environment.

Impact on Daily Life

The qualitative research shed light on the strategies implemented by students affected by these gaps:

Bandwidth management: Negotiating internet usage times with family members, attending classes with cameras turned off to save data, or downloading reading materials in the early hours of the morning.
Screen restrictions:** Those who rely exclusively on mobile phones report significant difficulties in writing long papers, consulting multiple sources simultaneously, and managing bibliographic tools, which directly impacts the quality of their assignments.

Conclusion and Public Policy Challenges

The results confirm that university inclusion policies oriented solely toward distributing computers or providing basic connectivity are insufficient. To prevent digitalization and hybrid education from becoming filters that amplify background inequalities, institutions must design comprehensive pedagogical strategies that train students in informational and strategic digital competencies, adapting to the heterogeneous reality of their student body.</p>
    </trans-abstract>
    <kwd-group xml:lang="es" kwd-group-type="author-generated">
      <kwd>brecha digital</kwd>
      <kwd>
educación superior</kwd>
      <kwd>
desigualdad</kwd>
      <kwd>habilidades digitales</kwd>
      <kwd>
América Latina 




</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
    <kwd-group xml:lang="en" kwd-group-type="author-generated">
      <kwd>Digital divide
Higher education
Inequality
Digital skills
Latin America</kwd>
    </kwd-group>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>xml-lang</meta-name>
        <meta-value>es</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
  </article-meta>
</front>
